Joshua Schermann

jschermann91@gmail.com | 218-232-7669 | Minneapolis, MN LinkedIn: shorturl.at/jktHJ | Portfolio: shorturl.at/wxFQS | Github: shorturl.at/nvGV5

Summary

Full stack web developer with a background in construction. I proved my development skills with my Certificate in MERN Full Stack Web Development from University of Minnesota. I am skilled in JavaScript, React, Express.js, MongoDB, and MySQL. My latest project, Code Savior, was a full stack web application used to share coding resources and take quizzes. I was lead developer in a team of three, and I organized workflow with a kanban board, built quiz functionality, and taught others how to connect Handlebars.js to a MySQL and Express.js back end. A friend introduced me to programming, and I took some lessons to find that I loved the sense of accomplishment in solving coding problems. I switched careers for new challenges and personal growth. I want to use my leadership experience, communication skills, and motivated work ethic learned from construction to succeed in software development.

Skills

Front End: React, HTML5, CSS, Bootstrap, Flexbox, Responsive Design

JavaScript: Node.js, jQuery, Handlebars.js, Jest, Mocha, AJAX, React, Object Oriented

Programming

Back End: Express.js, Model View Controller, RESTful APIs, Heroku

Databases: MySQL, NoSQL, MongoDB, Object Relational Mapping, Sequelize, Mongoose

Collaboration: GitHub, GitLab, Agile

Projects

Code Savior GitHub: shorturl.at/fDHW3 Deployment: shorturl.at/nuSXY

- Role: Lead Developer, JavaScript guiz creator
- Web application for sharing coding resources and taking coding quizzes.
- Users can make and delete posts, upvote posts, and take coding quizzes. I built the quiz functionality and designed back end structure.
- Technologies used: Handlebars.js, Express.js, Node.js, JavaScript, HTML, SASS, and Mocha.

Movie Me GitHub: shorturl.at/cxF04 Deployment: shorturl.at/xyJX1

- Role: Lead Developer, fetch API design
- Web application for getting movie recommendations.
- Wikipedia API is used to gather names of over 100 movies in different genres. My role was to build the API fetch requests by learning from Wikipedia API documentation.
- Technologies used: Open Movie Database API, Wikipedia API, HTML, JavaScript, CSS, Bulma CSS library.

Weather Watch GitHub: shorturl.at/gvISW Deployment: shorturl.at/coOTV

Role: Solo Project

• A web application used for displaying weekly weather information for different cities around the world.

- Client side storage is used for saving city search history.
- Technologies used: Open Weather API, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap

Work Experience

Viet and Co. Oct 2017 - Jun 2021

Pile Driver Rogers, MN

- Created foundation for Iversen Center for Faith underneath St. Thomas Aquinas Chapel while preserving 100 year old historic architecture with complex resistance pier underpinning.
- Coordinated workflow and motivated team with strict deadlines on massive construction projects.
- Calculated elevations and site layouts to engineer's specifications.
- Guided teams while operating pile hammers and drill rigs.
- Welded structures and shoring systems to match blueprints.

Ames Construction Apr 2014 - Oct 2017
Pile Driver Burnsvile, MN

 Completed Highway 36 bridge over Lexington Avenue in Roseville, teardown and rebuild in only 60 days, beating tight schedule and budget.

- Built over 20 bridges, read blueprints, calculated elevations and performed site layout.
- Led teams and communicated workflow with EFCO formwork and concrete pours.
- Assembled cranes and rigged loads as a Certified Rigger and Signaler.
- Operated forklift as Certified Powered Industrial Truck Operator.

Software Development Student

July 2021 - Present

Gap explanation

I resigned from my job in construction to pursue a career in software development. I spent three months studying JavaScript, CSS, and HTML on my own with Codecademy and FreeCodeCamp. In October 2021, I started MERN Full Stack Web Development at University of Minnesota to continue learning technologies needed to become a developer.

Education

Bachelor's Degree in Design in Architecture at University of Minnesota Jan 2014

Certificate in MERN Full Stack Web Development at University of Minnesota March 2022